Preliminary Guide to the Simmons & Waters Collection of Bookplates
Yale University Arts Library
Simmons & Waters Collection of Bookplates
1704-1898
BKP 75
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
This is a collection of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century bookplates, mostly European and armorial in style.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was purchased from Simmons & Waters, secondhand book and print dealers in England, in 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century bookplates, mostly European and armorial in style. The bookplates are all mounted on cards measuring 6 x 4.5 inches. Many of the mounts are inscribed with a number in the upper left on recto. A few of the bookplates have additional inscriptions or annotations.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Bookplates – Individuals. II. Bookplates – Institutions. III. Ephemera.
Bookplates are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Bookplates; Bookplates; Simmons & Waters
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains private bookplates arranged alphabetically by the patron's last name.
  - Abbott – Bartlett, 1895-1896 1898 undated; 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barton – Benyon, undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berkeley – Blencowe, 1894 1896 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blount – Bund, 1712 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Burgess – Cholmondeley, 1890 1897 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clanchy – Daking, undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Damer – Estcourt, 1769-1893 undated; 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Evans – Frazer, undated; 21 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Freeling – Gregory, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gunn – Heath, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hemming – Isaac, 1704 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jacques – Lees, 1768 undated; 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Leeson – Lyons, 1830-1895 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    This folder contains a series of five bookplates for the Count and Countess of Leiningen-Westerburg.
  - Mackarness – Molyneux, undated; 21 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Money-Kyrle – Palmer, 1894 undated; 20 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Park – Portman, 1782-1895 undated; 20 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    This folder contains a bookplate by Thomas Bewick for Robert Pinkney.
  - Powell – Selwyn, 1818 undated; 21 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Seymour – Stiebel, 1889 1894 undated; 20 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Strange – Towneley, undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Tucker – Watson, 1893 1895 undated; 21 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    General note
    This folder contains a bookplate by William Fowler Hopson for Margaret Van Zandt.
  - Waymouth – Wilkins, circa 1770 undated; 12 items (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Wilson – Zieber, 1890 undated; 19 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified, undated; 25 items (Box 3, Folder 23)
    This folder contains 25 bookplates with unidentified patrons. Most are armorial in style, although one monogram design and one pictorial are also included.
- Bookplates – Institutions, Series II
  This series contains various library, university, social organization, or business bookplates arranged alphabetically.
  - Bibliothecae monasterii Cremifanensis vulgo Kremsmünster – Worcester Diocesan Architectural & Archaeological Society, 1879-1894 undated; 9 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    This folder contains bookplates for the following organizations: Bibliothecae monasterii Cremifanensis vulgo Kremsmünster; Church House; Glenalmond College Library; House of Commons Library; Plymouth Free Public Library; Rectors of Hartlebury; Rubislaw House; Stourbridge Library; and Worcester Diocesan Architectural & Archaeological Society.
- Ephemera, Series III
  - Handwritten note, 1959; 1 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    This brief note describes a few details about the purchase of this collection.